Guide to the Corcoran Gallery of Art and Corcoran College of Art + Design, Corcoran Gallery of Art Development and Membership records 1869-2010 COR0003.2.RG
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Corcoran Gallery of Art and Corcoran College of Art + Design, Corcoran Gallery of Art development and membership records
circa 1869-2010
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
COR0003.2.RG
345 Linear Feet
The Membership Office was established in 1946, when the Trustees appointed the first Membership Secretary. The Trustees simultaneously created their own Committee on Membership. Attention in these early years seemed focused on sponsoring special events and activities and not necessarily on increasing financial contributions or the number of members. The Development and Membership Office Records trace the growth of that office's activities and responsibilities and witness its maturation into an autonomous department of the Corcoran Gallery of Art. Types of material in this record group include brochures, calendars, Congressional hearings and reports, correspondence, grant applications, meeting minutes, member and contributor lists, member and contributor record cards, memoranda, newsletters, pamphlets, reports, statistical data, and miscellaneous and ephemera items. Materials record information from 1869 through 1982 with the bulk of items dating after 1967.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is closed to research. Please see the Public Services and Instruction Librarian with any questions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Corcoran Institution Board of Trustees donated these records to The George Washington University in 2016.
Arrangement
Organized into 10 series: General correspondence and memoranda, "Chronological" files or "Blue" files, Subject files, Fundraising and membership solicitation, Three institution files, Corcoran School of Art, Reports/minutes/general texts, Statistics, Publications, and Unprocessed records
Historical narrative
The first section of this history, covering events through 1981, was prepared by Corcoran Archivist Katherine M. Kovocs for publication in 1985 with the support of the National Endowment for the Humanities.
The creation and expansion of the Development/Membership Office reflects a gradual increase in Gallery staff size as well as an increased professionalization of administrative tasks and responsibilities.
The Membership Office was established in 1946, when the Trustees appointed the first Membership Secretary. The Trustees simultaneously created their own Committee on Membership. Attention in these early years seemed focused on sponsoring special events and activities and not necessarily on increasing financial contributions or the number of members.
The Committee on Membership was abolished in 1954 and was not introduced until the late 1960s. The Membership Secretary post remained the same, but in 1959-1960 a new position, Assistant to the Director for Membership Development, was added to the staff. Membership underwent a more dramatic personnel change in 1961-62 with the creation of the Extension Services Department. The Department Supervisor was placed in overall charge of membership but was given a Membership Assistant to help carry out duties.
Membership and Development were a substantial part of the Corcoran's 1968 reorganization efforts. During the late 1960s the Trustees created a Trustee Committee on Development and Membership (the first use of the term, development). This served as an expanded version of the post-World War II Membership Committee. In addition, old staff positions were abolished and were replaced with new ones: a Director of Planning and Development, Development Assistants, and a Membership Secretary -- a position defunct since 1961.
The Membership and Development Office was expanded and changed further in the 1970s. The Director of Planning and Development post went through a succession of both titular and substantive changes. The original position was changed to Manager of Development (1969), Development Officer (1974), Director of Development and Membership (1978), and finally, Associate Director of the Gallery for Development and Membership (1980).
Lesser staff positions likewise have varied in title and function after 1967 to include Development Assistants, Membership Secretaries, Development Associates, and a Membership Manager.
The following section of this history was prepared in 2019 by George Washington University SCRC staff with the support of the Luce Foundation.
Following the contentious cancelling of the Robert Mapplethorpe exhibition "The Perfect Moment" in 1989, membership at the museum dropped, as well as donations to projects supported by the Development Office. Partially in response, a part-time membership and development consultant was hired in 1990.
In 1991, the museum began to actively look to fill the formerly vacant role of Director of Development. This position was filled in April 1991 under the title Vice President of Development and Public Affairs for the Corcoran Gallery. Duties undertaken by the Development office at this time included managing corporate donations and generating unrestricted income through public programs hosted at the Corcoran. The Development office also managed fundraising for exhibitions at the Corcoran and for the Annual Fund.
The office began a Deferred/Planned Giving Program in 1992 and in 1993 the Development office added a Corporate Affairs Officer. The office conducted a favorable review of Membership numbers in 1995, reflecting the success of the new telemarketing campaign, as well as the increased emphasis on corporate giving and partnerships.
In 2007 the Corcoran contracted Odell Simms & Associates for nine months to work on fundraising and development of several programs. By 2012, as the Corcoran Gallery of Art struggled with financial stability, the role of the Development office lessened as the Board focused on other efforts to create stable income for the Corcoran.
Custodial History
The records of the Membership and Development Office were transferred to the Archives from Corcoran storage areas, the Director's Office, and the Development/Membership Office in 1980 and 1981. Materials were largely unorganized. Some items were removed from the Director's Office records and have been placed with this record group. Clippings and photographs have been removed and filed with the history clippings files and the photographic records.
Post 1980 materials for the most part have not been deposited in or processed by the Archives at this time.
This note refers only to the processed portions of this collection.
Scope and Contents
The Development and Membership Office Records trace the growth of that office's activities and responsibilities and witness its maturation into an autonomous department of the Corcoran Gallery of Art. Types of material in this record group include brochures, calendars, Congressional hearings and reports, correspondence, grant applications, meeting minutes, member and contributor lists, member and contributor record cards, memoranda, newsletters, pamphlets, reports, statistical data, and miscellaneous and ephemera items. Materials record information from 1869 through 1982 with the bulk of items dating after 1967.
Although the files include materials on the late 19th and early 20th centuries; their frequency, type and content are limited. Before the 1940's the activities later performed by the Membership and Development Office were carried out sporadically by others, most notably the Director's Office. Information .on membership and fund raising activities through WWII, therefore, will most often be located among the Directors' and Trustees' Records. Some "Record Cards on Contributors" were created in the late 1940's for the period 1869-1947, however, and are located in these files. They record such information as donor name; amount (money) or title and value (work of art) of contribution; artist name, if applicable; and date of official trustee acknowledgement of receipt of the gift.
One can discern a distinctive group of Membership and Development files for the period 1948-1967, wherein are recorded the early appointment of individuals and Committees to membership tasks. Materials from these years follow the Gallery's experimentation with its still novel Membership Department. Records reveal an expansion of Membership Office activities to include some rudimentary fund raising efforts. They also show modifications in Development/Membership staff titles and office organization. Materials for these years are more numerous and diverse than for the earlier years described above. They include correspondence and memoranda, mostly from the 1960's; quarterly reports; and record cards on contributors. Subjects discussed and type of information contained include donations received, both monetary gifts and works of art; Membership activities films, lectures, functions; bulk mailings for membership recruitment; and statistical information (contained in the quarterly reports) on department budgets and costs, new members, membership categories, and corporate, foundation, and individual contributions. Prominent figures who appear in the files with various positions in the Membership Office for these years include Inga (Wall) Heck, Mrs. Walter Suter, Clifton R. Cummings, and Julie Forgey.
The records from 1968 on reflect the Development and Membership Office's growth into its current form. With the renewed committee in 1968 to improve and expand the Gallery, Membership Office duties and, more significantly, Planning and Development activities were greatly expanded. This growth is evident from the increased amount, diversity and content of post 1967 Membership and Development files. Materials for these years also demonstrate efforts to revise and improve upon membership and fund raising procedures. The files show that bulk mailings became more frequent and much more systematic; professional consultants were hired, advising on Development goals and directions; fund raising goals were outlined and procedures streamlined; the Development and Membership Office staff was changed and expanded; and a more successful system of trustee committee/Gallery staff participation in office-related duties was sought.
Subjects discussed and types of information contained include information on diverse aspects of individual, corporate and foundation donors; special membership and fund raising campaigns, e.g. Capital Fund Drive, Opportunities for the Corcoran Campaign, etc.; consultant files; publications--Corcoran Calendar, Corcoran Newsletter, various membership brochures; Three Institution Proposal; the Corcoran School of Art; statistical information on contributions, membership, and members/contributors; and various reports which record changes, progress, and new directions of the Membership and Development Office. Prominent figures appearing in the files for these years include John Lottes, Jillian Poole, Judith Levesque, Constance Broadstone, and Sheila Muccio. Though the Development and Membership Office records for these later years are the most complete for this record group, they are not exhaustive. The Director's Office records have retained some items pertinent to Membership/Development. The Melzac files, for example, include Manager of Development Jillian Poole's 1971 evaluation of the progress and accomplishments of her office since 1969.
Development and Membership materials have been divided into nine series according to subject or record type. The series are organized along a scale which progresses from primary-like to secondary-like files. Series which contain the more personal (primary) materials of the Development and Membership Office, e.g. General Correspondence and Memoranda, appear first. Those most removed from the personal element, e.g. Statistics, Reports, Meeting Minutes, etc., have been classed as secondary and are located at the end of the records. Subject series, often containing both types of items, make up the middle group of materials.
- General correspondence and memoranda, 1953-1980; Series 1
  Conditions Governing Access
  This series is closed to research. Please see the Public Services and Instruction Librarian with any questions.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains miscellaneous letters and memoranda inappropriate for placement in other series. Materials concern general Membership and Development issues, subjects and activities. Incoming and outgoing letters are arranged alphabetically; memoranda are organized chronologically.
  - General Correspondence, A-Z, 1967-1977; Series 1 (Box 1, Folders 1-9)
  - General Memoranda, Undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folders 10-16)
- "Chronological" files or "Blue" files, 1969 September-1980 August; Series 2
  This series contains photocopies or "blue" copies of memoranda and correspondence of CGA Director, Director of Development, Manager of Development, Membership Secretary, etc.; Membership and Development reports; 'various statistics; government grant proposals (NEA, NEH); meeting agendas; and miscellaneous textual materials. Chronological files postdating 1978 are more likely to contain all these various materials than earlier chronological records. Items are arranged chronologically by year, month, and day. It should be noted that, though at their inception these files were likely meant to be exhaustive, they are not complete. They have been retained primarily as a "back up" for other Development and Membership files in this record group.
  - Development/Membership, 1979 June-1980 August; Subseries 2 (Box 1, Folders 17-45)
  - Development/Membership, 1978 August-1979 May; Subseries 2 (Box 2, Folders 1-19)
  - Development/Membership, 1978 April-May; Subseries 2 (Box 2, Folders 20-22)
  - Development/Membership, 1976 March-1977 August; Subseries 2 (Box 2, Folders 23-34)
  - Development/Membership, 1978 June-July; Subseries 2 (Box 2, Folders 35-38)
  - Development/Membership, 1975 February-1976 February; Subseries 2 (Box 2, Folders 39-51)
  - Development/Membership, 1974 April-1975 January; Subseries 2 (Box 3, Folders 1-7)
  - Development/Membership, 1969 September-1971 May; Subseries 2 (Box 3, Folders 8-25)
- Subject files, 1952-1978; Series 3
  This series contains records of activities/issues/subjects of import to Development and Membership. All varieties and types of items concerning a subject should be located in each's subject file. Materials are arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Advertisements-Press, Undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - "American Collection" Catalog, 1967-1969; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Annual Fund, Undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Art Publications - Subscriptions/Exchanges, Undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Bicentennial Activities, Undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folders 30-31)
  - Board Luncheons, Undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - CGA Brochures, Undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Bulk Mailings - Cost Estimates, Undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Bulk Mailings - Mailing Companies, Undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Bulk Mailings - Memoranda, Undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Bulk Mailings - Schedules/Miscellaneous, Undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Bulk Mailings - Form Letters, 1952-1978; Series 3 (Box 3, Folders 38-39)
  - Business Committee for the Arts, Undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Capital Fund Drive - Case Statement, Undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Capital Fund Drive - Darcy Communications (Consultants), Undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Capital Fund Drive - Implementation Plan, Undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Capital Fund Drive - Prospects, Undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Capital Fund Drive - Don Smith (Consultant), 1970 June-1971 May; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Capital Fund Drive - Don Smith (Consultant), 1969 January-1970 May; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Capital Fund Drive - Survey, Undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Capital Fund Drive - Miscellaneous, Undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Chevy Chase Membership Drive, Undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Computers, Undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Consultants-Miscellaneous, Undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Copyrights, Undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Countdown, Undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Cultural Institutions A-Z, Undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folders 54-55)
  - D.C. Commission on the Arts & Humanities, Undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Friends, Undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folders 57-60)
  - Gale Associates (Consultants), 1969 April-1971 July; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Gale Associates (Consultants), 1966-1969 March; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Gale Associates (Consultants)-Report, Undated; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Information Booth, Undated; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Membership Drive, 1969-1970; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - National Steering Committee, Undated; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - New Members Receptions, Undated; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Open House, Undated; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Opportunities for the Corcoran Campaign-Benefit Dinner, Undated; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Opportunities for the Corcoran Campaign-Miscellaneous, Undated; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Soleri Exhibit-Luncheon, Undated; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Tax Exemptions and Deductions, Undated; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Travel Programs, Undated; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Washington Area Arts Co-op, Undated; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Washington Art Group, Undated; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Williams Memorial Fund, Undated; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Fund raising and membership soliciation, 1947-1982; Series 4
  Arrangement
  Organized into 5 subseries: Corporate solicitation, Foundation and grant solicitation, Grant proposals, Individual solicitation, and General Fundraising.
  - Corporate solicitation, 1967-1977; 1970-1977; Series 4 Subseries 1
    This subseries ontains memoranda, correspondence, meeting minutes of the Trustee Corporate Subcommittee, lists of CGA corporate members/contributors or possible members/donors, and miscellaneous materials on general corporate solicitation policies, procedures, etc. These materials are arranged alphabetically by corporate name or chronologically within types of material (see Container Listing).
    This subseries is closed to research. Please see the Public Services Librarian with any questions.
    - Women's Committee, Undated; Series 4 Subseries 1 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - American Security Bank, Undated; Series 4 Subseries 1 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Armco Steel Corp., Undated; Series 4 Subseries 1 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Comsat, Undated; Series 4 Subseries 1 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - IBM, Undated; Series 4 Subseries 1 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Philip Morris, Inc., Undated; Series 4 Subseries 1 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Riggs National Bank, Undated; Series 4 Subseries 1 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - B.F. Saul Co., Undated; Series 4 Subseries 1 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - J.R. Taft Corp., Undated; Series 4 Subseries 1 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Washington Gas Light Co., Undated; Series 4 Subseries 1 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Washington Post, Undated; Series 4 Subseries 1 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Woodward & Lothrop, Undated; Series 4 Subseries 1 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - General Companies A-z, Undated; Series 4 Subseries 1 (Box 4, Folders 29-37)
    - Corporate Subcommittee Meeting Minutes, Undated; Series 4 Subseries 1 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Memoranda, Undated; Series 4 Subseries 1 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Business Lists, 1969-1978; Series 4 Subseries 1 (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Business Lists, Undated, Series 4 Subseries 1 (Box 4, Folders 41-42)
    - Miscellaneous, Undated; Series 4 Subseries 1 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Foundation and grant solicitation, 1958-1982; 1970-1976; Series 4 Subseries 2
    This subseries contains memoranda, correspondence, lists of CGA foundation contributors or prospective donors, federal grant proposals (almost exclusively to National Endowment for the Arts), and miscellaneous items including some statistics, general memoranda, and materials on foundation/grant solicitation policies and procedures. It should be noted that because many of the foundation lists contain notations on individual foundations they can often be helpful in strengthening individual foundation files. In addition, one should also be aware that government grant proposal files ideally contain all pertinent items on each grant: grant application, award or rejection letter, acknowledgement letter, request for an advance or reimbursement, on each application's progress. However, most grant files are missing some of these items. The materials are arranged alphabetically by foundation name and in the case of government grants, chronologically, or chronologically within types of material (see Container Listing).
    This subseries is closed to research. Please see the Public Services Librarian with any questions..
    - Alcoa Foundation, Undated; Series 4 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - Alvord Foundation, Undated; Series 4 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - Atlantic Richfield Foundation, Undated; Series 4 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 46)
    - Cafritz Foundation, 1974; Series 4 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 47)
    - Cafritz Foundation, 1968-1970; Series 4 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 48)
    - Cummins Engine Foundation, Undated; Series 4 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 49)
    - Charles Delmar Foundation, Undated; Series 4 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 50)
    - Firestone Foundation, Undated; Series 4 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 51)
    - Ford Foundation, Undated; Series 4 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 52)
    - Graham Foundation, Undated; Series 4 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 53)
    - John Hechinger Foundation, Undated; Series 4 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 54)
    - Howard & Bush Foundation, Undated; Series 4 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 55)
    - Kresge Foundation, Undated; Series 4 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 56)
    - Andrew Mellon Foundation, Undated; Series 4 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 57)
    - Richard King Mellon Foundation-Budgets, Undated; Series 4 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 58)
    - Richard King Mellon Foundation-Correspondence, Undated; Series 4 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 59)
    - Richard King Mellon Foundation-Dinner, 1976 May; Series 4 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 60)
    - Richard King Mellon Foundation-Electrical Renovation, Undated; Series 4 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 61)
    - Richard King Mellon Foundation-Fire Alarm Installation, Undated; Series 4 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 62)
    - Richard King Mellon Foundation-Fire-Fighting Equipment, Undated; Series 4 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 63)
    - Richard King Mellon Foundation-Inspection of Gallery, Undated; Series 4 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 64)
    - Richard King Mellon Foundation-Report, 1974; Series 4 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 65)
    - Richard King Mellon Foundation-Security, Undated; Series 4 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 66)
    - Richard King Mellon Foundation-Miscellaneous, Undated; Series 4 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 67)
    - Eugene and Agnes Meyer Foundation, 1974; Series 4 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 68)
    - Eugene and Agnes Meyer Foundation, 1958-1964; Series 4 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 69)
    - Old Dominion Foundation, Undated; Series 4 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 70)
    - Olin Foundation, Undated; Series 4 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 71)
    - Marjorie Merriweather Post Foundation, Undated; Series 4 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 72)
    - Queene ferry Coonley Foundation, Undated; Series 4 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 73)
    - Rockefeller Foundation, Undated; Series 4 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 74)
    - Rohm & Haas Co., Undated; Series 4 Subseries 2 (Box 4, Folder 75)